

1800 102 2558 | +91 9818882211





OMPRAKASH A

OM PRAKASH A

OMPRAKASH A

CSM Scrum Master seeking roles in Software Development, Application

Programming, Application Maintenance, Project Management, Requirement

Analysis, Solution

Architecture, Agile, Scrum, Java, ASP. Net, IIS, HTML, XML, JavaScript, Python, Bitbucket, Jenkins, Git, Maven

Total Experience: 18 Year(s) 0 Month(s)

Highest Degree: MS/MSc(Science) [INFORMATION

Notice Period: 2 Months

TECHNOLOGY]

Current Designation: Scrum Master - Java

Current Company: Mphasis Ltd

Current Location: Chennai

 $Pref.\ Location: \textbf{Bengaluru/Bangalore,Chennai,Australia}$

Functional Area: IT Software - Application Programming /

Maintenance

Role: Project Mgr-IT/Software

Industry: IT-Software/Software Services

Marital Status: Single/unmarried

Key Skills: Scrum Master, Project Manager-IT/Software Development, Application Programming, Application

Maintenance, Project Management, Requirement Analysis, Solution

Architecture, Agile, Scrum, Java, ASP. Net, IIS, HTML, XWL, Java Script, Python, Bitbucket, Jenkins, Git, Maven

Verified : Phone Number | Email - id

Last Active: 20-Jan-21

Last Modified: 20-Jan-21

Jump to Section

Work Experience | Education | IT Skills | Projects |

Summary

Performance-driven professional with over 17 years of IT experience which includes 10 Years as Developer / QA and 7+ years as Scrum Master

Certified Scrum Master (CSM) from Scrum Alliance (Badge Id 996439)

In depth experience in scrum ceremonies - Scrum Meeting, Sprint Review and Retrospective meetings Leadership level experience in collaborating for product & sprint backlog, estimation, prioritization & user stories

In depth experience in MicroServices and Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) architectures Focused on timely deliverables within sprints with cross-functional team and ensuring that overall project is delivered within pre-set cost parameters

Performed the role of Agile coach for advocating and implementing Agile methodologies in new frontiers

Experience in CI/CD - Continuous Integration tools like Jira, Jenkins, Git, Maven

Received many awards, recognitions for outstanding performance on deliveries & process improvement initiatives

Work Experience

Mphasis Ltd as Scrum Master -Java Mar 2020 to Till Date

Client: Royal Bank of Scotland Period: Mar 2020 to Till Date Role: Scrum Master Location: Chennai Title: Lending Platform

Description: The Lending program is an initiative consisting of multi-release projects covering the Lending business function in RBS. It's aim is to provide an end-to-end process flow that creates new and handles existing lending application tasks, captures and adds lending decision-making functions. The system generates and stores documentation in the Enterprise Content Management (ECM) system.

Roles & Responsibilities:

Ensure the scrum team lives by the values and practices of Scrum

Coordinate with product owner in grooming the product backlog and its prioritization

Ensure the product backlog is completed and prioritized by the product owner before the sprint planning begins Encourage the team to discuss and negotiate each item in the sprint goal

Run the Daily Stand-up meeting to discuss team progress, announce daily commitments and highlight impediments Facilitate team members to get together after the Daily Stand-up, to discuss any technical/non-technical issues in detail Facilitate Sprint Review meeting and demo the work completed in the sprint and receive feedback from the business team

Facilitate Sprint Retrospective for the team to self-introspect and plan for improvements in the next sprint Play the role of a coach for the scrum team, helping them to become a high performing, productive team delivering quality product

Perform root cause analysis for undelivered stories in the previous sprint and for other issues

1

Important

 Using Free CV Search you have access to featured candidate profiles of Naukri. You can browse through the profiles and email the candidates of your choice directly using the email option provided. To prevent misuse of candidate information, contact details and attached resume of the candidates have been withheld. Discuss with the development team to identify if any motivation or commitment issues existed within the team and find

Driving the continuous improvement culture within the team

Risk identification and mitigation

Protect the scrum team from outside influences or distractions

Regular Jira review - Resolution of mapping issues between initiatives, epics, stories and tasks

Monitoring defect lifecycle and tracking it to closure

Take corrective measure based on the outcomes of 'Retrospective' session

Tech Mahindra Ltd. as Scrum Master

Nov 2002 to Mar 2020

Client: Nissan

Period: Nov 2019 to Mar 2020

Role: Scrum Master

Location: Trivandrum (Nissan client location)

Title: Spectra

Description: Spectra is a "Specification Tracking System" which would analyze and maintain the periods and deployment of various vehicle feature specifications. The source data goes through 'Data Ingestion', 'Data Engineering' and 'Data Visualization' layers and generates outputs to make critical business strategy and decisions.

Roles & Responsibilities:

Coordinate with Product Owner in grooming the project backlog and its prioritization

Facilitate for scrum ceremonies of Sprint planning, Daily stand-up, Sprint review and Retrospective meeting Identify motivational issues in development team members and find the root cause of it and address them

Coordinate with the Product Owner to perform backlog refinement, Burn-down chart tracking, issue resolution activities along with team

Coordinate to maintain Jira board with real-time status to generate reports on the health of the Project / Sprint to share it with all stakeholders

Coordinate with external stakeholders like Tech support, dependent project teams and managers of shared resources to ensure that the team is not distracted and stay focused

Coordinated for external validation of estimation provided by the team members as the team members had specific skill sets (Data - Ingestion, Engineering and Visualization)

Coach the business team and new team members on the Agile / Scrum methodologies for a seamless delivery experience for the entire team

Facilitating self-organized leadership culture in the scrum team and ensuring all members are aligned to the common goals of the team for a quality delivery of the project

Identified root cause and resolution plan if the 'Burn down' chart shows lag in planned deliveries

Coaching the product owner on creation and maintenance of the product & sprint backlog

Liaised between developers & product owner and facilitate conflict resolution if any

Keep an eye on the risk and impediments to proactively take risk mitigation action within time

Coordination for prioritization and resolution of defects

Client: Honeywell

Period: Nov 2018 to Oct 2019

Role: Scrum Master

Location: Bangalore (Honeywell client location)

Title: WESUI Dashboard

Description: WES is a Warehouse Execution System developed through micros services architecture in which each of the sub system is an individually replaceable component. The WES-UI is a dashboard which pertains to the development of various functional UI screens for the system using ReactJS and GraphiQL.

Roles & Responsibilities

Played the role of Scrum Master for Product teams with a focus on helping the team to help themselves and deliver quality product

Coach / Train the team on scrum principles and facilitate resolution of day to day operational issues

Applied creativity in ensuring that tasks were completed by the team without being pushed, forced and thrusted upon, more of a pull culture was encouraged

Facilitating self-organized leadership culture in the scrum team and ensuring all members are aligned to the common goals of the team for a satisfactory delivery of the project

Leveraged the technical knowledge on microservices architecture, CI/CD, API, Java, Cucumber, Jenkins, Bitbucket, Git, Postman, Swagger, Maven, Eureka to effectively coordinate among the scrum team members

Ensured protection to team from external impediments, distractions and conflicts so that focus is only on delivery of value in the sprint

Maintained:

Team velocity & sprint progression and communicated it to all stakeholders

Product and sprint 'Burn down' chart with planned and actual trajectory

Identified root cause and resolution plan if the 'Burn down' chart shows lag in planned deliveries

Coaching the product owner on creation and maintenance of the product & sprint backlog.

^ Back to Top

Education

UG: B.B.A/ B.M.S (Management) from Madras University in 1998

PG: MS/M.Sc(Science) (INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY) from Allagappa University in 2002

^ Back to Top

IT Skills

Skill Name	Version Last Used Experience
Java, ASP.net, IIS, HTML, XML	
JavaScript, Python, CMS	
JIRA	
Bitbucket, Jenkins, Git, Maven	
Eureka, Swagger	

Java, Selenium, Cucumber	
SOAP-UI, Postman	
Jira, HP-QC, HP-ALM, Mantis	
Bugzilla, Whizible	
Agile, Waterfall, Iterative	
Oracle, SQL Server, MS-Access, MySQL	

^ Back to Top

Languages Known

Language	Proficiency	Read	Write	Speak
English	Expert	✓	✓	✓
Tamil	Expert	✓	✓	✓
Telugu	Expert			✓

^ Back to Top

Projects

Project Title: Lending Platform Client: Royal Bank of Scotland Nature of Employment: Full Time

Duration: Mar 2020 - Till Date Onsite / Offsite: Offsite

Project Details: The Lending program is an initiative consisting of multi-release projects covering the Lending business function in RBS. It's aim is to provide an end-to-end process flow that creates new and handles existing lending application tasks, captures and adds lending decision-making functions. The system generates and stores documentation in the Enterprise Content Management (ECM) system.

Roles & Responsibilities:

Ensure the scrum team lives by the values and practices of Scrum

Coordinate with product owner in grooming the product backlog and its prioritization

Ensure the product backlog is completed and prioritized by the product owner before the sprint planning begins

Encourage the team to discuss and negotiate each item in the sprint goal

Run the Daily Stand-up meeting to discuss team progress, announce daily commitments and highlight impediments Facilitate team members to get together after the Daily Stand-up, to discuss any technical/non-technical issues in detail Facilitate Sprint Rev

Project Title: Spectra

Client: Nissan

Nature of Employment: Full Time

Duration: Nov 2019 - Mar 2020 Onsite / Offsite: Offsite

Project Details: Description: Spectra is a Specification Tracking System which would analyze and maintain the periods and deployment of various vehicle feature specifications. The source data goes through Data Ingestion, Data Engineering and Data Visualization layers and generates outputs to make critical business strategy and decisions.

Roles & Responsibilities:

Coordinate with Product Owner in grooming the project backlog and its prioritization

Facilitate for scrum ceremonies of Sprint planning, Daily stand-up, Sprint review and Retrospective meeting Identify motivational issues in development team members and find the root cause of it and address them

Coordinate with the Product Owner to perform backlog refinement, Burn-down chart tracking, issue resolution activities along with team

Coordinate to maintain Jira board with real-time status to generate reports on the health of the Project / Sprint to share it with all stakeholders

Coordinate with external stakeholders like Tech support

Project Title: WESUI Dashboard

Client: Honeywell

Nature of Employment: Full Time

Duration: Nov 2018 - Oct 2019 Onsite / Offsite: Offsite

Project Details: Description: WES is a Warehouse Execution System developed through micros services architecture in which each of the sub system is an individually replaceable component. The WES-UI is a dashboard which pertains to the development of various functional UI screens for the system using ReactJS and GraphiQL.

Roles & Responsibilities:

Played the role of Scrum Master for Product teams with a focus on helping the team to help themselves and deliver quality product

Coach / Train the team on scrum principles and facilitate resolution of day to day operational issues

Applied creativity in ensuring that tasks were completed by the team without being pushed, forced and thrusted upon, more of a pull culture was encouraged

Facilitating self-organized leadership culture in the scrum team and ensuring all members are aligned to the common goals of the team for a satisfactory delivery of the project

Leveraged the technical knowledge on microservices architecture, CI/CD, API, Java, Cucumber, Jenkins

Project Title: SAP Enterprise System (Run & Maintenance)

Client: LyondellBasell Inc.

Nature of Employment: Full Time

Duration: Jun 2013 - Oct 2018

Onsite / Offsite: Offsite

Project Details: Description: Lyondell Basells IT division delivers new SAP Enterprise level projects & enhancements every quarter and based on business need would deliver off-cycle (non-quarter release) projects & enhancements. This on-site Scrum Master role is to deliver these releases following scrum methodology to ensure high quality & within the project budget.

Roles & Responsibilities:

Focused on creating and sustaining a dynamic and safe environment for the scrum team that fosters the development opportunities and motivates the high performance amongst the team members

Facilitated sprint planning, retrospective and review meetings

Applied creativity in ensuring that tasks were completed by the team without being pushed, forced and thrusted upon, more of a pull culture was encouraged

Instituted self-driven leadership culture in the scrum team and ensuring all members are aligned to the common goals of the team for a satisfactory delivery of the project

^ Back to To

Affirmative Action

Work Authorization

Physically Challenged: No

Job Type: Permanent Employment Status: Full time

^ Back to Top

Careers - About Us - Clients - Terms & Conditions - FAQ's - Contact Us - Report a Problem - Site Map - Resources
Our Partners: Jeevansathi Matrimonials - ICIClcommunities.org - 99acres - Real Estate In India
All rights reserved © 2021 Info Edge India Ltd.

Careers - About Us - Clients - Terms & Conditions - FAQ's - Contact Us - Report a Problem - Site Map - Resources
Our Partners: Jeevansathi Matrimonials - ICICIcommunities.org - 99acres - Real Estate In India
All rights reserved © 2021 Info Edge India Ltd.